<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | The &micro;Blog
]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-22T15:22:59-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[K-SID]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Python Scripts from Dropbox on the Raspberry Pi]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/2014/01/27/running-python-scripts-from-dropbox-on-raspberry-pi/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-27T22:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/2014/01/27/running-python-scripts-from-dropbox-on-raspberry-pi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever tried writing code on your Raspberry Pi from just the plain terminal window then you&rsquo;ve probably used Nano or Vim. If you&rsquo;re like me you wished you could have used your favorite IDE or text editor on another machine. When I develop for the Raspberry Pi my normal use case is to SSH in and write code via Nano. While this works just fine I&rsquo;d prefer to have the bigger real estate afforded by my desktop monitors.</p>

<h3>What is <code>preheat</code></h3>

<p><code>preheat</code> is my solution to this problem. It allows me to pull scripts down from my Dropbox account at execution time. When I finally decided I didn&rsquo;t want to code directly on the Pi anymore the very first thing that came to my mind was to install <a href="http://dropbox.com">Dropbox</a> on the Pi and just have it sync with a folder on my dev machine. It only took a few searches to realize that a Dropbox client for the Pi doesn&rsquo;t exist. So I found a few other solutions like <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rsync">rsync</a>, <a href="http://owncloud.org">ownCloud</a> and others but everything I found was either too much work or just plain overkill for what I needed. So <code>preheat</code> was born.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a simple Python script that will query your Dropbox account for the file you want to run and pull it down. So normally I&rsquo;d use the following to run a script I&rsquo;m working on:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>sudo python myscript.py
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>With <code>preheat</code> I would run it like this:</p>

<p><div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='bash'><span class='line'>sudo python preheat myscript.py
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t need to have <strong>myscript.py</strong> on the Raspberry Pi. It&rsquo;s on my desktop machine in a dropbox folder being updated every time I change it. When I run it via <code>preheat</code> it will scan my Dropbox account, find it, and pull it down for me.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like to see how it works <a href="https://github.com/sidwarkd/preheat">check out the source code on Github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
