<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Eagle | The &micro;Blog
]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/blog/categories/eagle/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/"/>
  <updated>2014-03-01T23:52:39-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[K-SID]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Eagle How-To: Export Board Image]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/2013/11/03/eagle-how-to-export-board-image/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-03T00:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/2013/11/03/eagle-how-to-export-board-image</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes when you&rsquo;re working on a board design you don&rsquo;t want to wait to get a prototype board from a fab house. For simple or one off boards you can just make them at home. In order to do that we need a way to get our board design out of Eagle and onto a PCB. Most home-etch processes I&rsquo;ve seen require, in some form, a to-scale printout of the board. Personally I use the <a href="http://www.pcbfx.com/">Pulsar PCB products</a> which I&rsquo;ve found to work very well. The following is my process for getting the board design printed out.</p>

<ol>
<li>  Launch Eagle and open the board view of your project.</li>
<li>  Turn the grid off via the <strong>View->Grid</strong> menu or using the command: &ldquo;grid off&rdquo;</li>
<li>  Turn off all layers except the the ones that you want to print. I like to see layers 1, 17, 18 and 20. That&rsquo;s top, pads, vias and dimension. If your board is two sided you only want to print one side at a time.</li>
<li>  If the background is black we need to make it white. Do this via the <strong>Options->User Interface</strong> dialog or use the command: &ldquo;set palette white;window;&rdquo;.</li>
<li>  File->Export->Image</li>
<li>  Select a destination file. I prefer to use the .png format.</li>
<li>  Check the <strong>Monochrome</strong> checkbox</li>
<li>  Change the resolution to a multiple of your screen dpi. The default screen resolution in Windows is 96 dpi so I normally use 384 which is 96 x 4.</li>
<li>  Click <strong>Ok</strong> to export the image.</li>
</ol>


<p>  You now have an image file of your board that should scale perfectly to size. I normally just drag it into a document in OpenOffice Writer. If it goes into your document full size you just need to scale it to 25% of original size and it will be perfectly to-scale.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
