<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: beginner | The &micro;Blog
]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/blog/categories/beginner/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/"/>
  <updated>2014-02-01T23:36:02-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[HardlySoftware]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Love for the Beginners]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.microcasts.tv/blog/2013/08/19/some-love-for-the-beginners/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T21:41:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.microcasts.tv/blog/2013/08/19/some-love-for-the-beginners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>&ldquo;Read the Datasheet Again!&rdquo;</h3>

<p>That&rsquo;s what somebody told me on a forum once for not seeing a piece of information in a 90 page datasheet.  If there is one thing I&rsquo;ve learned after many years of doing hobbyist electronics it&rsquo;s that the various forums are NOT friendly places for beginners. I&rsquo;m subscribed to receive notices from multiple forums and everyday I see beginners taking heat for &ldquo;not reading the datasheet&rdquo; or &ldquo;not searching the forum.&rdquo;  It always amazes me how condescending people can be and how quickly they forget that at some point we were all beginners.</p>

<h3>Friend of Foe, You Choose</h3>

<p>I wish people would understand one simple fact.  It takes just as long to be a jerk as it does to make a new friend online.  Instead of answering somebody&rsquo;s questions with a condescending tone why not take the same amount of time to encourage and support.  Is is so hard to remember that everybody is on a different level as far as experience and knowledge go?  A lot of beginners have no idea that the answer is on page 73, paragraph 6 of the datasheet and publicly shaming them does nothing but boost your own shallow ego.  I&rsquo;m not sure why smart technical people who stereotypically faced a lot of bullying growing up turn to preying on people just looking for a little help.</p>

<h3>Play Nice</h3>

<p>So why the blog post?  Well, it really comes down to a simple thought.  Can we please just play nice?  Can we show some love to the beginners?  Next time you see a &ldquo;stupid noob&rdquo; question in a forum, step up and help out.  Welcome them to the community and please, whatever you do, don&rsquo;t treat him/her like an illiterate waste of your time because that &ldquo;idiot&rdquo; is an actual person on the other side of the interwebs just looking for some help.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
